
<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->

<chapter id="sec_intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <sect1 id="Features">
    <title>Features</title>
    <para><application>Matita</application> is an interactive theorem prover
      (or proof assistant) with the following characteristics:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It is based on a variant of the Calculus of (Co)Inductive Constructions (CIC). CIC is also the logic of the Coq proof assistant.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>It adopts a procedural proof language, but it has a new set of small step tacticals that improve proof structuring and debugging.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>It has a stand-alone graphical user interface (GUI) inspired by
CtCoq/Proof General. The GUI is implemented according to the state
of the art. In particular:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>It is based and fully integrated with Gtk/Gnome.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>An on-line help can be browsed via the Gnome documentation browser.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <!--<para>Mathematical formulae are rendered in two dimensional notation via MathML and Unicode.</para>-->
            <para>Mathematical formulae are rendered via Unicode.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <!--
      <listitem>
        <para>It integrates advanced browsing and searching procedures.</para>
      </listitem>-->
      <listitem>
        <para>It allows the use of the typical ambiguous mathematical notation by means of a disambiguating parser.</para>
      </listitem>
      <!--
      <listitem>
        <para>It is compatible with the library of Coq (definitions and proof objects).</para>
      </listitem>
      -->
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="WrtCoq">
    <title>Matita vs Coq</title>
    <para>
      The system shares a common look&amp;feel with the Coq proof assistant
      and its graphical user interface. The two systems have variants
      of the same logic,
      close proof languages and similar sets of tactics. <!--Moreover,
      Matita is compatible with the library of Coq.-->
      From the user point of view the main lacking features
      with respect to Coq are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>proof extraction;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>an extensible language of tactics;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>automatic implicit arguments;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>several ad-hoc decision procedures;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>several rarely used variants for most of the tactics;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>sections and local variables. <!--To maintain compatibility with the library of Coq, theorems defined inside sections are abstracted by name over the section variables; their instances are explicitly applied to actual arguments by means of explicit named substitutions.--></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Still from the user point of view, the main differences with respect
      to Coq are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the language of tacticals that allows execution of partial tactical application;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>the unification of the concept of metavariable and existential variable;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>terms with subterms that cannot be inferred are always allowed as arguments of tactics or other commands;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>ambiguous terms are disambiguated by direct interaction with the user;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>theorems and definitions in the library are always accessible without needing to require/include them; right now, only notation needs to be included to become active, but we plan to remove this limitation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
